<!DOCTYPE Article PUBLIC "-//GNOME//DTD DocBook PNG Variant V1.0//EN"[
<!ENTITY version "0.8"> 
]>

<article id="index">
 <artheader> 
  <title>Bug-Buddy</title>
  <copyright>
   <year>2000</year>
   <holder>Jacob Berkman</holder>
  </copyright>
  <copyright>
   <year>2000</year>
   <holder>Telsa Gwynne</holder>
  </copyright>
 <!-- translators: uncomment this:
   <copyright>
    <year>2000</year>
    <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
   </copyright>
    -->

  <legalnotice>
   <para>
     Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
     document under the terms of the <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation
     License</citetitle>, Version 1.1 or any later version published
     by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections, no
     Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. You may obtain a copy
     of the <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation License</citetitle> from
     the Free Software Foundation by visiting <ulink type="http"
     url="http://www.fsf.org">their Web site</ulink> or by writing to:
     Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330,
     Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.
   </para>
   <para>
     Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their products and
     services are claimed as trademarks. Where those names appear in any
     GNOME documentation, and those trademarks are made aware to the members
     of the GNOME Documentation Project, the names have been printed in caps
     or initial caps.
   </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <releaseinfo> 
    Manual version 0.2: changed licence to FDL, re-ordered to suit new
    order of the pages in the program itself. 
  </releaseinfo>
 </artheader>

 <sect1 id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title> 

  <para>
    The <application>bug-buddy</application> program is a tool which
    will guide you through making a bug report as painlessly as possible.
    You can alter things at any stage, and then either send, save, or
    abandon the resulting report. This document describes
    version &version; of <application>bug-buddy</application>.
  </para>

  <para>
    <application>bug-buddy</application> can be started in a variety
    of ways:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Open the <guimenu>main GNOME menu</guimenu> and select
      <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Programs</guimenu>
       <guisubmenu>Utilities</guisubmenu>
       <guimenuitem>Bug Report Tool</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      .
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
      Run <command>bug-buddy</command> at the prompt in a terminal such
      as <application>gnome-terminal</application> or
      <application>xterm</application>.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
      If you are using the <application>GNOME file manager</application>,
      gmc, you can double-click your mouse on a core file to start it.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
      When a GNOME program experiences a bad crash, a <guilabel>crash
      dialogue box</guilabel> is displayed. If <application>bug-buddy</application>
      is present on the system, then one of the options in the dialogue
      box will be to make a bug-report. Selecting that will lead you
      to a further dialogue box giving you details of the program which
      crashed. Continuing at this stage will invoke <application>bug-buddy
      </application>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    <application>bug-buddy</application> is a very structured program.
    At any stage you can continue forward or head backwards to correct
    earlier details.
  </para>

  <para>
    The aim of all this is to be able to collect all the information
    which a developer will need to reproduce the same problem and be
    able to fix it. Some of the information generated may look a bit
    off-putting, but don't delete it. It will be useful.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="contact-info">
  <title>Contact information</title>

  <para>
    <application>bug-buddy</application> first asks for these pieces
    of information, in order to be able to send the report correctly.
    It makes very good guesses so you should be able to skip straight
    ahead. 
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Your name</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       GNOME works this out itself, but if you want to change it you
       can do this here.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Email address</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Again, GNOME should work this out. You should not need to change
       this unless you normally fetch your mail from another account. In
       that case, you may wish to put your other account here, so that
       any responses to the bug go to that address.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Full path of sendmail</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       This allows you to check that bug-buddy is looking in the right
       place when it tries to send email. You will almost certainly not
       need to change this. 
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

  <para>
    There is an <guibutton>About</guibutton> button in the lower corner,
    which provides access to an About box and to
    <ulink type="http" url="http://www.bug-buddy.org">
    bug-buddy's home on the web</ulink>. 
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="report-info">
  <title>Report Information</title>

  <para>
    The options which show up here vary according to which of the
    drop-down options you select. Sometimes it is much more helpful
    to add information to an existing report than to start a new one.
    (And sometimes you realise you forgot something in one of your
    earlier reports, and you want to add it.) You can search the bug 
    trackers for 
    <ulink type="http" url="http://bugs.gnome.org">GNOME</ulink>,
    <ulink type="http" url="http://bugs.kde.org">KDE</ulink>,
    <ulink type="http" url="http://bugs.debian.org">Debian</ulink> or
    <ulink type="http" url="http://bugs.helixcode.com">Helix Code</ulink>
    to find a relevant bug report and note down the number. 
  </para>

  <para>
    If you select <guibutton>Add more information to existing
    report</guibutton> then you will be prompted for the bug number of
    the existing report.
  </para>

  <para>
    If you select <guibutton>Create a new bug report</guibutton> then you
    will be prompted for the package number, the package version, the
    bug severity and the class of bug:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Bug tracking system</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       <application>bug-buddy</application> can send reports to several
       different places. A drop-down list is available here. Currently
       you can report bugs to the bug-trackers of KDE, GNOME, Debian
       GNU/Linux, Helix Code, and to independent projects if they use
       a bug-tracking system that <application>bug-buddy</application>
       understands.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>


   <varlistentry>
    <term>Package</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       You can search through the drop-down list for the correct package
       to assign this bug to. If you know the exact filename of the program
       you ran, and you use rpms, you can use the command <command>rpm -qf 
       <filename>/full/path/to/file</filename></command> to verify which
       package it came from. If you use Debian, you can use the command 
       <command>dpkg -S <filename>/full/path/to/file</filename></command>.
       To find out the full pathname to, say, gnome-terminal, or
       kfloppy, you can use the command <command>which</command>: 
       <command>which gnome-terminal</command> or <command>which 
       kfloppy</command>. 
     </para>
     <para>
       If you are still not sure which package to assign a bug to, searching
       the bug-trackers on the web by keyword to find out where other
       people have assigned it in the past can be very helpful.
     </para>
     <para>
       Because there are so many possible packages, the drop-down list is
       split alphabetically. Clicking on a package beginning with 'a',
       for example, will give you a further selection of several other 
       apps beginning with 'a'. So you will need to double-click on a
       package and then look at the sub-categories to find some packages.
     </para>
     <para>
       If you do not select a package, it will be left as 'general'. This
       will get through to the bug-tracking system, but someone there will
       have to manually assign it a package, which slows its progress 
       down. 
     </para>
     <caution>
      <para>
        If you do not put a package name here, many bug-trackers send back 
        automatic "Please assign a package next time" responses. Some of
        them will drop the report.
      </para>
     </caution>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Version</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Once you have decided on a package, checking its version number
       is much simpler. For GNOME and KDE programs, it will often be in
       the 'About' box of a program.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Severity</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       There are different severities of bugs you can assign. If you 
       are not sure, normal is fine. There should not be that many 
       critical or grave bugs in software which is in daily use. They
       tend to get fixed fast. So it is probably unlike you will need
       those two categories. Before assigning bugs to those two, you really
       should get the latest stable version and check it has not already
       been fixed.
     </para>

     <para>
       These descriptions are adapted from the Debian bug tracker
       <ulink type="http" 
       url="http://bugs.debian.org/Bugs/Developer#severities">severity
       definitions</ulink>:
     </para>

     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Critical</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
          This bug makes unrelated software on the system (or the whole 
          system) break, or causes serious data loss, or introduces a 
          security hole on systems where you install the software. Examples
          would be hanging the entire machine or overwriting files it should
          not even touch. 
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Grave</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
          This bug makes the software in question unusable or mostly so, 
          or causes data loss, or introduces a security hole allowing 
          access to the accounts of users who use the software. A program
          which consistently crashes on startup or produces files called
          <filename>core</filename> in your home directory might well be 
          grave. 
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Normal</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
          This is what you will usually want: the default value.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Wishlist</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
          This is a useful category for two things: very hard to fix
          bugs; and requests for features or enhancements. ("It would be
          nice if...")
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Class</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       The default class of a bug is a software bug: "there is something
       wrong with the program". This is almost always the class to select.
       Sometimes this is not quite what you need. You can change the class 
       to a few other things: the most common alternative to need is a
       documentation bug: anything from typos to absent or out of date 
       documentation. 
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="description">
  <title>Description</title>
  <para>
    The <guilabel>Short subject for the bug report</guilabel> section
    will be used as the "Subject" header of the emailed bug report. 
    You do not need the package name in it as you have already assigned 
    that. But being specific is good. "Crash when I try to save" or 
    "Forgets my preferences" is much better than "Bug". Hackers will 
    read these summaries when looking for something they can fix, and 
    clear one-sentence summaries will catch their attention. You must
    fill this in. If you do not, <application>bug-buddy</application>
    will tell you to.
  </para>

  <para>
    The <guilabel>Full description of the bug</guilabel> section is where
    you describe what you did, what happened, and what you expected to
    happen. You must fill this in, too, or
    <application>bug-buddy</application> will tell you to. Good things to 
    include:
  </para>
   
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Exact copies of any error messages;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Your window manager name and version (especially if the bug involves 
      moving things around the screen or mouse focus problems);
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      If you can make it happen in one way, and not in another way,
      include that. If there are two ways to do something (a menu
      selection and a typed command, for example), and only one triggers
      the bug, definitely include that;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Why you think it is a bug. What should have happened instead?
      Whilst this is obvious for some things, ("It shouldn't crash when
      I try to save the file") it is not obvious for others. Give a
      better way for the program to behave. ("If it can't save the file, 
      it should tell me so that I don't keep editing it without realising 
      I am wasting my effort".)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Sometimes screenshots can help demonstrate bugs. Please do not send one
      in a bug-buddy report! But if you have one, mention that you have it,
      so that a bug-fixer who would like to see it can email you about it.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    If you have any suggestions on what caused it or how to fix it,
    wonderful. If not, don't worry. Just explain what happened. If
    a developer needs more information, s/he can mail you back for
    it. 
  </para>

  <para>
    If you have a (short!) text-file which contains information of use
    you can include it here, too. If you have a small HTML file which
    crashes your editor, or two sets of options for a program where one
    works and the other doesn't, these are the sort of things to include
    here. Just put the name of the file into the <guilabel>Include a 
    text file</guilabel> box at the bottom. 
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="debug-info">
  <title>Debugging Information</title>

  <para>
    You will have to pick one of the three options here. 
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Skip this step</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       If you are reporting a documentation bug, or reporting a bug which
       doesn't crash the program, or reporting a bug and you don't have a
       core file associated with it, select this option and disregard the
       next page of this guide. This is the default option. 
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Collect debugging information from a crashed application</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       If <application>bug-buddy</application> began because you said
       yes to "Report a bug" in a dialogue box telling you something had
       crashed, select this. If you do so, you will be prompted for
       two things. These should be filled in ready for you. If they 
       are not:
     </para>
     
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
         <guilabel>Binary</guilabel>: In this box you must type the
         name of the program as you would type it at the command-line.
         For example, if the <application>Control Center</application>
         crashed, you would need to type <command>gnomecc</command> here.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
         <guilabel>Process ID</guilabel>: In this box you must type
         the process ID or <acronym>PID</acronym>. This will probably
         be available from the original dialogue box where you selected
         "Report a bug". If you have closed that window, you can find it
         by starting the <application>Gnome System Monitor</application> 
         through selecting
          <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Programs</guimenu>
           <guisubmenu>Utilities</guisubmenu>
           <guimenuitem>System Monitor</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
         or typing <command>gtop</command> at the command line. You
         will find the PID in the left-hand column and the command
         in the right hand column (you may need to scroll right for this
         column to be visible).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Collect debugging information from a core file</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       If <application>bug-buddy</application> began because you 
       double-clicked on a file named <filename>core</filename> in the
       file manager, select this. Also select this if you have a core file
       which you know was created as a result of the bug you are reporting.
       An extra box will appear where you can tell it where the core file
       lives.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="collect-debug-info">
  <title>Collecting debugging information</title>
  <para>
    This page may look rather unnerving. You will see it if you have
    selected "Collect information from a crashed application" or 
    "Collect information from a core file" in the previous page. 
  </para>
  <para>
    When the application crashed, a copy of all the
    details of what the program was doing was frozen. This was either dumped
    to the core file or held in place. What <application>bug-buddy</application>
    is doing is to go through all that information and find out what steps
    the program took to get to the stage where it crashed. Programmers
    can follow the rather cryptic output and work out where something
    started to go wrong. This output will be automatically attached to 
    your bug report. Don't edit it down unless you really know what you are
    doing.
  </para>
  <para>
    Sometimes <application>bug-buddy</application> will not be able to
    generate the information and tell you that it cannot recognise the
    core file. If so, simply continue to the next stage. Do 
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> send the core file itself as an alternative. 
    It is only the output that bug-buddy wants.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="system-config">
  <title>System Configuration</title>

  <para>
    There are certain details which bug-fixers always want to know about
    your system. These are not details which will reveal private information
    about your computer. <application>bug-buddy</application> goes and looks 
    for the details on your machine. You can see exactly what it collects 
    in the main window. If you happen to be using something which 
    you know is different, you can alter the details here. You shouldn't
    need to.
  </para>

  <para>
    If you don't want to see this every time you use the program, you can
    select the <guibutton>automatically go to next page when complete</guibutton>
    option. If you do this and later want to go back and check, you can use
    the <guibutton>Back</guibutton> option from the <link
    linkend="report-info">Reporting Information</link> section to get back
    here.
  </para>
 </sect1>



 <sect1 id="submit-report">
  <title>Submitting the Report</title>
  <para>
    Once you have finished your report, you can review the report and
    decide what to do with it. You will probably want to submit it to 
    the bug-tracking system, but if you want to send it elsewhere for
    some reason, you can. You can choose from:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Submit bug report</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Selecting this and clicking on <guibutton>Next</guibutton>
      will email the bug report to the bug tracker. You can send
      yourself a copy by clicking the relevant checkbox here. If
      you are submitting the report to an independent bug tracker,
      you will need to fill in the submission address yourself. 
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Only send report to yourself</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       This will send the bug report to you. If you changed the
       email address at the start, then it will use the new
       address.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Save report to file</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Selecting thing will produce a box for you to give the
       name of a file to save the bug report to. If the file already
       exists, it will ask you whether to overwrite the file or not.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <para>
    <application>bug-buddy</application> will tell you what it has
    done with your bug report. That's it.
  </para>
  <para>
    Thank you for reporting your bug.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="bugs">
  <title>Known bugs and limitations</title>

  <para>
    <application>bug-buddy</application> has very few bugs or limitations.
    Currently known:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      There is an applet called <application>Tick-A-Stat</application>
      which can be set to look for core files and timestamp them with
      their origin and date. <application>bug-buddy</application> cannot
      read files which <application>Tick-A-Stat</application> has done
      this to. 
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="authors">
  <title>Authors</title>

  <para>
    <application>bug-buddy</application> was written by Jacob Berkman
    (<email>jberkman@andrew.cmu.edu</email>). To find more information
    about it, please visit 
    <ulink type="http" url="http://www.bug-buddy.org">
    bug-buddy's home on the web</ulink>.
  </para>

  <para>
     Please send all comments, suggestions, and bug reports to the
     <ulink url="http://bugs.gnome.org" type="http">GNOME bug
     tracking database</ulink>. The package is of course bug-buddy.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    This guide was written by Telsa Gwynne 
    (<email>telsa@linuxchix.org</email>). Please send all comments
    and suggestions regarding it to the GNOME Documentation Project 
    at <email>docs@gnome.org</email>. Some parts of this document
    (the definitions of "grave", "critical", and so on) are directly
    derived from the Debian bug tracker <ulink type="http" 
    url="http://bugs.debian.org/Bugs/Developer#severities">severity
    definitions</ulink> and other pages.
  </para>

  <!-- For translations: uncomment this:
   <para> Latin translation was done by ME
     (<email>MYNAME@MYADDRESS</email>). Please send all comments
     and suggestions regarding this translation to SOMEWHERE.
   </para> 
     -->
 </sect1>
</article>
